Oh Jordan you probably answered this
question in many ways but I kind of find
it overwhelming to see to come across
the kind of information that you and
Daniel schmuck Tim Berger said it should
have release its I find it hard to know
what to do in the short term in terms of
effective altruism but also in the long
term as someone who's like 29 has a
fairly clean slate in terms of the next
10 years it's just I was wondering if
you could offer any guidance for because
it can seem quite overwhelming and also
urgent they kind of all the different
threats that are going on that you guys
talk about so I was just kind of an open
question yeah I can okay yeah okay so I
think that the that we now are in a
circumstance for some of the things that
I have not been able to articulate
effectively in the past can be
articulated much more effectively and
that has to do with the fact that change
is strictly nonlinear there are small
amounts of change that happened during
ordinary times and large amounts of
change that happened during
extraordinary times I personally I'd
like to use the stoic Chronos Kairos
distinction because I feel like it's a
very rich mythopoetic way of talking
about it so in many ways that the
appropriate movement is a movement of
preparation and then surge or action
during the periods of Chronos when time
is moving an ordinary pace you need to
be engaging in upgrading your own
capacities locally the chains of trust
that you've developed your own
sovereignty and ability to respond to
what's happening your own sense making
and discernment be able to perceive
reality you Chronos is a period of time
to be able to prepare yourself to engage
for when the the storm has broken in the
wars upon you Kairos is the time to
actually use those resources and move
and make aggressive movements into the
possibility space with all that you've
put together the inverse is an exercise
in either wasted resources or magical
thinking
many many people endeavor to exercise
Kairos action during Chronos time and
they can get very frustrated because
they want to make big change they see
the big change needs to happen and they
try very very hard to push that big
heavy
up the side of the cliff but it's a very
inefficient effort and sometimes you
must do it sometimes you have to do in
which case you know I hope that you're
successful but broadly speaking you'll
be crushed into that effort and
therefore it's not a model of saying
only do the work all right no it's do
the work because the moment will come
and when the moment comes then act does
that make sense
mm-hmm the moment has come so now it's
time to say oK you've done the work
let's hope you've done the work now
start stepping into it how much can be
built now when the energy is available
in open somebody actually sent me a very
interesting query directed to the men
men look around you look at your friends
your male friends and this by the way it
could be elders as well as youngers who
among them would you feel very
comfortable marrying your daughter who
among them would you be very comfortable
covering your back in a fight where
people are gonna die who among them
would you entrust that the tutelage of
the raising of your son if you die if
the answer is none of them you done
fucked up better fix it
you got a lot of them then you're ready
to move you've got a team because that's
the kind of stakes that's the way to
feel into it if you've got a strong
immediate sense of that answer you could
just imagine in your mind I'm a friend
of yours and be able to ask those three
questions and just nod yep I don't even
know why I can say yes but it's there
it's very clear and very easy then you
were a tuned instrument you're now
prepared to be put to use that's it
because simple as that now from that
point start looking around for those
people gather them around you
among them begin to discover what is
yours to do collectively what can you do
where are you it could be anything you
know there's people doing all kinds of
stuff right now you can be figuring out
things that are very very local
worst-case scenario just make sure that
you and your own are very well taken
care of because if things get very bad
you don't want to be making choices out
of fear you know I don't know about
everybody else on this call but I
noticed that there was a period of time
where everybody kind of had to unstuck
themselves from complacency and being in
a in a bad spot to getting into a place
of some level security actually called a
bucket one when I was calling people I
was like hey what bucket are you in
right now I need you to be in bucket
three where are you oh you're in bucket
one all right well you know finish dry
and picking up your mom and dad and
bringing coming out to the farm and
making sure you got food and water call
me when you've got your shit together
and by the way now you're in bucket to
bucket too is your solid if you've kind
of done whatever you needed you to
transition to a state of readiness for
the environment that you're in but now
you're looking around what is the thing
that I need to be doing generally
speaking that's kind of a tactical
mindset and it may be the bucket two is
where you're supposed to be you're
supposed to be in a tactical location
there's holes for you to dig there's
code for you to write there's things for
you to do that your hands run right now
bucket three is a strategic disposition
now you're actually in a situation where
the fires on the ground you're able to
actually step back from the things that
are going on and look around either
because that's your position in the
environment or because it's your natural
disposition but you can start looking
around saying hey what are the questions
that need to be asked in the context
that we're in how do I ask these
questions and how do I come to create
contexts where I can actually begin to
answer these questions in a way that is
appropriate to descrip of what we're
dealing with I can go and do more detail
Matt if you like again I think we should
come back to it I think one one thing
that people might want to ask is does
that apply to women as well or what's
the don't know I'm not a woman I hope I
hope I hope there's a good answer to
that question that could be a good
inquiry
what's the similar thing for for the
questions that I expected that as an
extraordinary power flow inquiry and
once it is fully discovered things will
change meaningfully for the better
[Music]
you